Guide to the Daniel Huntington Study Portrait Photographs Collection ca. 1870-1890 PR 256
New-York Historical Society
Daniel Huntington Study Portrait Collection
ca. 1870-1890
New-York Historical Society
PR 256
0.42 Linear feet (141 photographs, 12 folders)
The collection holds 141 portrait photographs used by Huntington for his study of the subjects painted by him.
Provenance
Gift of Charles R. Huntington, April 9, 1908.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Daniel Huntington (1814-1906) was educated at Hamilton College. He studied panting with Samuel Morse and Henry Inman in New York City. He primarily painted portraits and landscapes. Huntington was president of the National Academy of Design, and Vice-President of the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
Scope and Content Note
Two years after Daniel Huntington's death, his son Charles Richards Huntington (1847-1915) presented the New-York Historical Society with a collection of 141 portrait photographs used by his father "for his study of the subjects painted by him." Each of the men (and the single woman, Mary McCrea Stuart) in the collection is represented by one or more portrait photographs which had been blown-up to life-size dimensions, sometimes made from a previously existing negative or one made of an earlier photograph. In the case of sitters who died before the advent of paper photography, images were taken from daguerreotypes. The enlargements were mounted on a stiff paperboard and roughly trimmed almost to the shape of the subject's head. Each of the portraits has the sitter's surname in pencil on the verso; some have a shorthand clue to an occupation, profession, title, or institutional affiliation. These annotations, if contemporary to Huntington or his son, have been transcribed in the box and folder list that follows. Many of the photographs have a puncture at their top, most likely from the nail Huntington used to tack them up in view of his easel.
The sitters are familiar to students of nineteenth-century New York: they include prominent bankers, merchants, industrialists, educators, financiers, generals, lawyers, judges, politicians, government officials, and men of the cloth. The photographs are generally not dated. Several note that they were made from daguerreotypes and a few mention particular photographers, or are mounted on the backs of printed boards from photographers' studios. The images that are dated range from the 1870s (Henry Potter) to the 1890s (Kelly, Gracie, Schurz, and Sheldon). Photographers mentioned are Bogardus (Adams, Arthur) and Sarony (Tilden), with one annotated by Huntington as having been taken in his studio (Sherman). Eight of the portraits are mounted on the verso of stamped boards from the Rockwood Studio (Brown, Gracie, Johnston, Henry Potter, Taft, and Weir) or Kurtz (Dodge Sr. and Hostetter) in New York. In addition, the portrait of Henry Codman Potter is mounted on the verso of a large photograph of Calvary Baptist Church, on West Twenty-third Street.
Oil portraits of these sitters are now in the New York Chamber of Commerce Collection at the New York State Museum, the Smithsonian Institution, Metropolitan Museum of Art, the American Museum of Natural History, New York Public Library, Harvard University, Vassar College, and West Point Museum, among other institutions. The New-York Historical Society owns more than twenty portraits painted by Huntington. Other portraits remain in private collections, including those of social clubs, hospitals, corporations, and the families who commissioned them from the artist.
Arrangement
Photographs are filed alphabetically by sitter; life dates and vocations were added during processing.
Photographic prints.; Portraits.; Men -- Portraits.; Huntington, Daniel, 1816-1906
- Portraits
  Scope and Contents note
  Portraits are filed alphabetically by sitter; life dates and vocations were added during processing.
  - unspecified
    - Adams, William (1813-1897), clergyman (Box Unknown container 331 for instance of Adams, William (1813-1897), clergyman, Folder 1)
      General note
      On verso:(taken by Bogardus photographer)
    - Arthur, Chester Alan (1830-1886), politician (Box Unknown container 332 for instance of Arthur, Chester Alan (1830-1886), politician, Folder unknown container)
    - Aspinwall, William Henry (1807-1875), businessman (Box Unknown container 333 for instance of Aspinwall, William Henry (1807-1875), businessman, Folder unknown container)
    - Avery, Samuel Putnam (1822-1904), art dealer, philanthropist (Box Unknown container 334 for instance of Avery, Samuel Putnam (1822-1904), art dealer, philanthropist, Folder unknown container)
    - Babcock, Samuel D. (1822-1902), banker (Box Unknown container 335 for instance of Babcock, Samuel D. (1822-1902), banker, Folder unknown container)
    - Beardsley, Samuel (1790-1860), judge, politician (Box Unknown container 336 for instance of Beardsley, Samuel (1790-1860), judge, politician, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: (perish commerce perish credit)
    - Blatchford, Samuel (1820-1883), judge (Box Unknown container 337 for instance of Blatchford, Samuel (1820-1883), judge, Folder unknown container)
    - Booth, Henry Matthias (1843-1899), clergyman, educator (Box Unknown container 338 for instance of Booth, Henry Matthias (1843-1899), clergyman, educator, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: of Auburn [Theological Seminary]
    - Brown, James (1791-1877), banker (Box Unknown container 339 for instance of Brown, James (1791-1877), banker, Folder unknown container)
    - Brown, James M. (1820-1890), banker (Box Unknown container 340 for instance of Brown, James M. (1820-1890), banker, Folder unknown container)
    - Bruce, George (1781-1866), typefounder (Box Unknown container 341 for instance of Bruce, George (1781-1866), typefounder, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: from daguerreotype
    - Cameron, James Donald (1833-1918), politician (Box Unknown container 342 for instance of Cameron, James Donald (1833-1918), politician, Folder 2)
      On verso: Senator Cameron, Sec of War
    - Chittenden, Simeon Baldwin (1814-1889), merchant (Box Unknown container 343 for instance of Chittenden, Simeon Baldwin (1814-1889), merchant, Folder unknown container)
    - Clark, Luther C. (d. 1877) (Box Unknown container 344 for instance of Clark, Luther C. (d. 1877), Folder unknown container)
    - Colgate, Robert (1812-1885), merchant (Box Unknown container 345 for instance of Colgate, Robert (1812-1885), merchant, Folder unknown container)
    - Coxe, Arthur Cleveland (1818-1896), clergyman (Box Unknown container 346 for instance of Coxe, Arthur Cleveland (1818-1896), clergyman, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: Bishop of Western New York (Buffalo)
    - Curtiss, Cyrus (d. 1879), merhcant [2 images] (Box Unknown container 347 for instance of Curtiss, Cyrus (d. 1879), merhcant [2 images], Folder unknown container)
      On verso: of Washington Life Insurance Co.?
    - Davis, Noah (1818-1902), judge (Box Unknown container 348 for instance of Davis, Noah (1818-1902), judge, Folder unknown container)
    - Dodge, William E., Sr. (1805-1883), merchant (Box Unknown container 349 for instance of Dodge, William E., Sr. (1805-1883), merchant, Folder unknown container)
    - Dodge, William E., Jr. (1832-1903), businessman [2 images] (Box Unknown container 350 for instance of Dodge, William E., Jr. (1832-1903), businessman [2 images], Folder unknown container)
    - Drisler, Henry (1818-1897), educator (Box Unknown container 351 for instance of Drisler, Henry (1818-1897), educator, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: Prof
    - Dwight, Theodore W. (1822-1892), educator [3 images] (Box Unknown container 352 for instance of Dwight, Theodore W. (1822-1892), educator [3 images], Folder unknown container)
      On verso 1 & 2: of Columbia Law School; on verso 3: of Law School Columbia
    - Edwards, Henry Pierrepont (1809-1855), judge (Box Unknown container 353 for instance of Edwards, Henry Pierrepont (1809-1855), judge, Folder 3)
      On verso: (from a Daguerre)
    - Field, Benjamin Hazard (1814-1893), philanthropist (Box Unknown container 354 for instance of Field, Benjamin Hazard (1814-1893), philanthropist, Folder unknown container)
    - Field, Cyrus West (1819-1892), capitalist [2 images] (Box Unknown container 355 for instance of Field, Cyrus West (1819-1892), capitalist [2 images], Folder unknown container)
      On verso #2: capital likeness D.H.
    - Fry, Charles M. (1822-1892), merchant, bank president (Box Unknown container 356 for instance of Fry, Charles M. (1822-1892), merchant, bank president, Folder unknown container)
      See: Folder 12
    - Frelinghuysen, Frederick Theodore (1817-1885), politician [2 images] (Box Unknown container 357 for instance of Frelinghuysen, Frederick Theodore (1817-1885), politician [2 images], Folder unknown container)
    - Gallatin, Albert (1761-1849), politician, diplomat (Box Unknown container 358 for instance of Gallatin, Albert (1761-1849), politician, diplomat, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: from a daguerreotype
    - Gardiner, John Lyon (1841-1920), gentleman (Box Unknown container 359 for instance of Gardiner, John Lyon (1841-1920), gentleman, Folder unknown container)
    - Garrison, Cornelius K. (1809-1885), businessman [2 images] (Box Unknown container 360 for instance of Garrison, Cornelius K. (1809-1885), businessman [2 images], Folder unknown container)
      On verso: "Com"[modore]
    - Gracie, James King (1840-1903), philanthropist (Box Unknown container 361 for instance of Gracie, James King (1840-1903), philanthropist, Folder unknown container)
    - Hallgarten,Julius (1842?-1884), banker (Box Unknown container 362 for instance of Hallgarten,Julius (1842?-1884), banker, Folder 4)
      On verso: from the small photo
    - Hamilton, Alexander, Jr. (1816-1889), lawyer (Box Unknown container 363 for instance of Hamilton, Alexander, Jr. (1816-1889), lawyer, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: afterward President of Astor Library Trustees
    - Hastings, Thomas S. (1827-1911), clergyman (Box Unknown container 364 for instance of Hastings, Thomas S. (1827-1911), clergyman, Folder unknown container)
    - Hayes, Rutherford Birchard (1822-1893), politician [3 images] (Box Unknown container 365 for instance of Hayes, Rutherford Birchard (1822-1893), politician [3 images], Folder unknown container)
      On verso #2: after his presidency
    - Hoffman, Eugene Augustus (1829-1902), clergyman, educator [2 images] (Box Unknown container 366 for instance of Hoffman, Eugene Augustus (1829-1902), clergyman, educator [2 images], Folder unknown container)
      On verso: Dean Hoffman
    - Hoffman, Samuel Verplanck (1802-1880), lawyer (Box Unknown container 367 for instance of Hoffman, Samuel Verplanck (1802-1880), lawyer, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: father of Dean H. of the Seminary
    - Hostetter, David Herbert (1819-1888), manufacturer (Box Unknown container 368 for instance of Hostetter, David Herbert (1819-1888), manufacturer, Folder unknown container)
    - Hunt, Wilson G. (1804-1892), merchant (Box Unknown container 369 for instance of Hunt, Wilson G. (1804-1892), merchant, Folder unknown container)
    - Jacobi, Abraham (1830-1919), doctor, educator (Box Unknown container 370 for instance of Jacobi, Abraham (1830-1919), doctor, educator, Folder 5)
    - James, Daniel Willis (1832-1907), merchant (Box Unknown container 371 for instance of James, Daniel Willis (1832-1907), merchant, Folder unknown container)
    - Jesup, Morris Ketchum (1830-1908), financier [2 images] (Box Unknown container 372 for instance of Jesup, Morris Ketchum (1830-1908), financier [2 images], Folder unknown container)
    - Johnston, John Taylor (1820-1893), railroad president (Box Unknown container 373 for instance of Johnston, John Taylor (1820-1893), railroad president, Folder unknown container)
    - Jones, John Divine (1814-1895), businessman (Box Unknown container 374 for instance of Jones, John Divine (1814-1895), businessman, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: Pres of Atlantic Ins. Co.
    - Kelly, Eugene (1806-1894), banker (Box Unknown container 375 for instance of Kelly, Eugene (1806-1894), banker, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: 1891
    - Kelly, William (1807-1872), philanthropist (Box Unknown container 376 for instance of Kelly, William (1807-1872), philanthropist, Folder unknown container)
    - Kendrick, Henry L. (1812-1891), educator (Box Unknown container 377 for instance of Kendrick, Henry L. (1812-1891), educator, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: of West Point
    - Kennedy, Robert Lenox (1822-1887), banker [2 images] (Box Unknown container 378 for instance of Kennedy, Robert Lenox (1822-1887), banker [2 images], Folder unknown container)
      On verso #2: too severe - but very like
    - King, Richard (d. 1891), businessman (Box Unknown container 379 for instance of King, Richard (d. 1891), businessman, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: Prest of Bank of Commerce
    - Lauterbach, Edward (1844-1923), lawyer, politician (Box Unknown container 380 for instance of Lauterbach, Edward (1844-1923), lawyer, politician, Folder 6)
    - Lenox, James (1800-1880), philanthropist (Box Unknown container 381 for instance of Lenox, James (1800-1880), philanthropist, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: This is quite large enough rather larger than life
    - Lincoln, Robert Todd (1843-1926), lawyer, politician (Box Unknown container 382 for instance of Lincoln, Robert Todd (1843-1926), lawyer, politician, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: (son of Prest Lincoln Secy of War)
    - Low, Abbot Augustus (1843-1912), inventor (Box Unknown container 383 for instance of Low, Abbot Augustus (1843-1912), inventor, Folder unknown container)
    - Low, Seth (1850-1916), educator, politician [2 images] (Box Unknown container 384 for instance of Low, Seth (1850-1916), educator, politician [2 images], Folder unknown container)
      On verso #1: when Prest of Columbia
      On verso #2: Pres. Columbia University & Mayor of N.Y. & Bklyn
    - Lyman, Theodore Benedict (1815-1993), clergyman (Box Unknown container 385 for instance of Lyman, Theodore Benedict (1815-1993), clergyman, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: Bishop of N Carolina
    - McGee, James (d. 1898), businessman (Box Unknown container 386 for instance of McGee, James (d. 1898), businessman, Folder unknown container)
    - McLane, James Woods (1839-1912), doctor, educator (Box Unknown container 387 for instance of McLane, James Woods (1839-1912), doctor, educator, Folder unknown container)
      See: oversize
    - Martin, Charles Jackson (d. 1888), businessman (Box Unknown container 388 for instance of Martin, Charles Jackson (d. 1888), businessman, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: Prest Home Insurance
    - Mills, Darius Ogden (1825-1910), banker (Box Unknown container 389 for instance of Mills, Darius Ogden (1825-1910), banker, Folder unknown container)
    - North, Edward (1820-1903), educator (Box Unknown container 390 for instance of North, Edward (1820-1903), educator, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: Prof Ham College
    - Nye, Ezra (1798-1866), sea captain (Box Unknown container 391 for instance of Nye, Ezra (1798-1866), sea captain, Folder unknown container)
      [from a daguerreotype]
    - Owen [Owens?], Thomas J. (d. 1881?), shipping merchant (Box Unknown container 392 for instance of Owen [Owens?], Thomas J. (d. 1881?), shipping merchant, Folder 7)
      On verso: painted June 1882 taken from another (much earlier) photograph
    - Parker, Amasa Junius (1807-1890), judge (Box Unknown container 393 for instance of Parker, Amasa Junius (1807-1890), judge, Folder unknown container)
    - Phelps, John Jay (1810-1869), merchant (Box Unknown container 394 for instance of Phelps, John Jay (1810-1869), merchant, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: father of Wm Walter Phelps [1839-1894]
    - Phelps, Royal (1809-1884), merchant (Box Unknown container 395 for instance of Phelps, Royal (1809-1884), merchant, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: he was in bad health & died soon after this was taken
    - Pierrepont, Henry Evelyn (1808-1888), philanthropist (Box Unknown container 396 for instance of Pierrepont, Henry Evelyn (1808-1888), philanthropist, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: of Brooklyn NY
    - Potter, Henry Codman (1834-1908), clergyman (Box Unknown container 397 for instance of Potter, Henry Codman (1834-1908), clergyman, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: of Grace [Church] (about 1875)
    - Prentice, Ezra Parmalee (1797-1876), businessman (Box Unknown container 398 for instance of Prentice, Ezra Parmalee (1797-1876), businessman, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: of Albany
    - Prime, William Cowper (1825-1905), lawyer, educator (Box Unknown container 399 for instance of Prime, William Cowper (1825-1905), lawyer, educator, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: V Prest of Metr Mus of Art
    - Pruyn, Robert Lansing (1825-1906), businessman (Box Unknown container 400 for instance of Pruyn, Robert Lansing (1825-1906), businessman, Folder unknown container)
    - Raven, Anton Adolph (1843-1919), businessman (Box Unknown container 401 for instance of Raven, Anton Adolph (1843-1919), businessman, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: of Atlantic Mutual Ins Co.
    - Ray, Robert (1794-1879), banker (Box Unknown container 402 for instance of Ray, Robert (1794-1879), banker, Folder unknown container)
    - Rolston, Roswell Graves (1838-1898), businessman (Box Unknown container 403 for instance of Rolston, Roswell Graves (1838-1898), businessman, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: Prest Farmers Loan & Trust Co.
    - Roosevelt, Theodore Sr. (1831-1878) (Box Unknown container 404 for instance of Roosevelt, Theodore Sr. (1831-1878), Folder unknown container)
    - Sage, Henry Williams (1814-1897), businessman, philanthropist (Box Unknown container 405 for instance of Sage, Henry Williams (1814-1897), businessman, philanthropist, Folder 8)
      On verso: of Ithaca
    - Schermerhorn, William Colford (1821-1903), philanthropist (Box Unknown container 406 for instance of Schermerhorn, William Colford (1821-1903), philanthropist, Folder unknown container)
    - Schurz, Carl (1829-1906), politician, diplomat (Box Unknown container 407 for instance of Schurz, Carl (1829-1906), politician, diplomat, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: 1899
    - Schwab, Gustav (1822-1888), businessman (Box Unknown container 408 for instance of Schwab, Gustav (1822-1888), businessman, Folder unknown container)
    - Scott, Thomas A. (1823-1881), railroad man (Box Unknown container 409 for instance of Scott, Thomas A. (1823-1881), railroad man, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: of Philada (before his paralysis)(good likeness)
    - Sheldon, James O. (1823-1907), banker (Box Unknown container 410 for instance of Sheldon, James O. (1823-1907), banker, Folder unknown container)
    - Sheridan, Philip Henry (1831-1888), military (Box Unknown container 411 for instance of Sheridan, Philip Henry (1831-1888), military, Folder unknown container)
    - Sherman, John (1823-1900), politician [2 images] (Box Unknown container 412 for instance of Sherman, John (1823-1900), politician [2 images], Folder unknown container)
      On verso #1: taken in my studio DH
      On verso #2: taken when Secy of the Treasury
    - Sibley, Hiram (1807-1888), industrialist, philanthropist (Box Unknown container 413 for instance of Sibley, Hiram (1807-1888), industrialist, philanthropist, Folder 9)
      On verso: (died July 1888)
    - Silliman, Benjamin (1805-1901), lawyer (Box Unknown container 414 for instance of Silliman, Benjamin (1805-1901), lawyer, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: Council for Bank of Commerce too old (when taken) but about right for him now 1888 / yes-good yet in 1898
    - Smith, Gerrit (1797-1874), philanthropist (Box Unknown container 415 for instance of Smith, Gerrit (1797-1874), philanthropist, Folder unknown container)
    - Stokes, James Boutler (1804-1881), banker (Box Unknown container 416 for instance of Stokes, James Boutler (1804-1881), banker, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: father of Anson Phelps Stokes
    - Stranahan, James Samuel Thomas (1808-1898), politician (Box Unknown container 417 for instance of Stranahan, James Samuel Thomas (1808-1898), politician, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: (of Brooklyn)
    - Stuart, Robert L. (1806-1882), merchant, philanthropist [3 images] (Box Unknown container 418 for instance of Stuart, Robert L. (1806-1882), merchant, philanthropist [3 images], Folder unknown container)
    - Stuart, Mary McCrea [Mrs. Robert L.] (d 1891), philanthropist (Box Unknown container 419 for instance of Stuart, Mary McCrea [Mrs. Robert L.] (d 1891), philanthropist, Folder unknown container)
    - Sturges, Jonathan (1802-1874), merchant (Box Unknown container 420 for instance of Sturges, Jonathan (1802-1874), merchant, Folder unknown container)
    - Sutherland, Jabez Gridley (1825-1902), judge (Box Unknown container 421 for instance of Sutherland, Jabez Gridley (1825-1902), judge, Folder unknown container)
    - Taft, Alphonso (1810-1891), politician (Box Unknown container 422 for instance of Taft, Alphonso (1810-1891), politician, Folder unknown container)
    - Thomas, Lewis (d. 1880), grain merchant (Box Unknown container 423 for instance of Thomas, Lewis (d. 1880), grain merchant, Folder 10)
      On verso: (of Produce Exchange)
    - Thompson, David (d. 1871?), businessman (Box Unknown container 424 for instance of Thompson, David (d. 1871?), businessman, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: NY Life & Trust?
    - Tibbits, George Moritimer (1796-1878), gentleman (Box Unknown container 425 for instance of Tibbits, George Moritimer (1796-1878), gentleman, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: Troy [NY]
    - Tilden, Samuel Jones (1814-1886), politician [2 images] (Box Unknown container 426 for instance of Tilden, Samuel Jones (1814-1886), politician [2 images], Folder unknown container)
      On verso #1: fm Saronys port photo
    - Tracy, Edward H. (d. 1875), engineer (Box Unknown container 427 for instance of Tracy, Edward H. (d. 1875), engineer, Folder unknown container)
    - Travers, William Riggin (1819-1887), financier (Box Unknown container 428 for instance of Travers, William Riggin (1819-1887), financier, Folder unknown container)
    - Trimble, George Thomas (1793-1872), merchant (Box Unknown container 429 for instance of Trimble, George Thomas (1793-1872), merchant, Folder unknown container)
    - Trimble, Merritt (1824-1903), banker (Box Unknown container 430 for instance of Trimble, Merritt (1824-1903), banker, Folder unknown container)
      On verso: "Bank for Savings" N.Y.
    - Vail, Henry F. (1812-1881), banker [2 images] (Box Unknown container 431 for instance of Vail, Henry F. (1812-1881), banker [2 images], Folder unknown container)
      On verso: Prest Bank of Commerce
    - Vail, Thomas Hubbard (1812-1889) (Box Unknown container 432 for instance of Vail, Thomas Hubbard (1812-1889), Folder unknown container)
    - Vanderbilt, Cornelius II (1843-1899) [2 images] (Box Unknown container 433 for instance of Vanderbilt, Cornelius II (1843-1899) [2 images], Folder unknown container)
      On verso #1: does not do him justice too old & severe
      On verso #2: not long before his attack [1896] a strong likeness